Guide to the Records of the Interfaith Council of Washington Square College 1948-1970 RG 39.4
New York University Archives
Records of the Interfaith Council of Washington Square College
1948-1970
RG 39.4
New York University Archives
3.0 linear feet 35 linear inches (7 boxes)
The records are those kept by the IFC secretary from its inception in 1956 through its final dissolution in 1970. The bulk of the records are from 1956 through 1969. In 1967, an IFC self-study recommended that the IFC's role be re-examined. In 1970, it was dissolved and superceded by a Committee on Faith and Life at NYU, established under the Office of Student Affairs.
School of Social Work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged categorically in eight series which include minutes, correspondence, publicity materials, and brochures.
The records are organized into eight series:
Predecessors of the Interfaith Council
Interfaith Council Meetings
Reports
Budget
Correspondence
Activities
Personnel and Space
University Administration
Separated Material
Sixteen inches of duplicate material was removed from the collection and discarded. Photographs have been separated from the collection.
Scope and Content Note
This collection of records from the Interfaith Council at Washington Square includes the IFC's meeting minutes, activities, publicity, correspondence, building business, and correspondence from the university administration. The bulk of the records are from 1956 through 1969. The records consist of 35 linear inches of minutes, correspondence, publicity materials, and brochures.
The records are those kept by the IFC secretary from its inception in 1956 through its final dissolution in 1970. The records of the IFC can provide valuable information to the researcher about the various religious groups at the Washington Square campus. The changes in the IFC's member organizations and in the types of programs they sponsored illustrate an important aspect of NYU student life over an eleven year period (1956-1967). This collection illustrates the change in religious composition and consciousness of the Washington Square student community and provides the researcher with evidence of the changes which took place in the issues with which the student body was concerned.
Historical Note
In 1947, New York University rented and renovated 2 Washington Square North as a religious center with quarters for the Christian Association (later re-named the University Christian Foundation), the Jewish Culture Foundation, the Newman Club, and the Library of Hebraica and Judaica. Between 1948 and 1956, the building was maintained by the House Committee which consisted of representatives from the clergy, professors, and students involved in the Washington Square religious organizations. This committee was responsible for setting policies regarding the use of the building and insuring its proper maintenance.
The Board of management also operated between 1948 and 1956. This board consisted of clergy, faculty, and student representatives. Chaired by Dean Thomas Pollock of Washington Square College, the board was responsible for setting general policies regarding the religious groups on campus and for coordinating their activities.
In March 1956, as the result of the University Self-Study, President Carroll Vincent Newsom established the Interfaith Committee. It immediately replaced the Board of Management and a few months later, when a resident manager was appointed, the House Committee was dissolved. Members of the Interfaith Committee (the name was changed in 1957 to the Interfaith Council) were appointed by the president of the university. The IFC consisted of 12 members, including three from the NYU Board of Chaplains, three religious directors, three faculty members at large, and three students. The goals of the IFC were to develop ties and cooperation between the religious groups on campus and between the religious groups and the university, to encourage student attendance at religious services, and to study the needs of religious groups to adjust the university budget to accommodate them.
During the 1940s and early 1950s there was an Interfaith Council at the Altschul House on the Heights campus. It was dissolved before the IFC at Washington Square was created and was reactivated in 1969 -- just as the Washington Square IFC was dissolved. The Washington Square and University Heights religious groups were in contact with one another but other than occasional courtesies (such as when Washington Square first moved in to 2 Washington Square North the Altschul House at the Heights sent them a couch), the two campuses' religious organizations were not connected.
The IFC employed a secretary and a resident manager. These were full-time positions which ran from September through June. They were usually taken by part-time students.
The IFC began with only the Protestant, Catholic, and Jewish organizations as its members. In the 1960s, its character changed to include Hindu, BaHai, and other groups. In its first few years, the IFC sponsored ecumenical discussions, art shows, and dinners. In the late 1960s, it sponsored a series of lectures on the draft and aided the Gay Liberation group in disputes with the university administration.
In 1961, the IFC adopted a resolution to support the building of the "Interfaith Triangle Center at Washington Square." This was to consist of three separate buildings for the Protestant, Catholic, and Jewish groups located in a triangle around the Loeb Student Center on Washington Square South. This proposal was in response to the need felt for greater space. They believed that the close proximity of these three buildings would maintain the opportunity for interfaith cooperation while providing each group with more space.
In the summer of 1964, the Catholic Center at 58 Washington Square South was opened. They continued to keep one room at 2 Washington Square North in order to maintain their ties with the other groups. The University Christian Foundation and the Jewish Culture Foundation were never able to build their buildings. In late 1978, the School of Social Work moved into 2 Washington Square North, the JCF moved into new quarters in Loeb Student Center, and the UCF moved into a room in 21 Washington Place.
In 1967, in recognition of the profound changes in the student body since the IFC's inception in 1956, the IFC proposed that a new self study be conducted. Its goal was to explore ways of including a wider range of religious groups in interfaith activities, to create a closer relationship between the religious groups at the Heights and at Washington Square, and also to examine the role of religion in the entire university. This study was carried out during the 1969-1970 academic year. In 1970, the IFC was dissolved and a Committee on Faith and Life at NYU under the Office of Student Affairs was created.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection. Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted. Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
Provenance
In 1980, the records of the Interfaith Council (IFC), 1948-1970, were donated to the NYU archives by the School of Social Work, who found the records when moving into the offices in 2 Washington Square North, which had previously been occupied by the IFC.
National Conference of Jews and Christians (U.S.).; New York University. Library of Judaica and Hebraica.; New York University.; Newman Club.; Newsom, Carroll Vincent, 1904-; Office of Student Affairs.; Pollock, Thomas Clark, 1902-; School of Social Work.; University Christian Foundation.; Wingate, Isabel Barnum; Brochures.; Correspondence.; Minutes.; Publicizing.; Washington Square |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series 1: Predecessors of the Interfaith Council, 1948-1956
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains the minutes and correspondence relevant to the operation of the House Committee and the Board of Management. These two bodies governed 2 Washington Square North between 1948 and 1956, prior to the creation of the IFC.
  - House Committee, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Management, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Interfaith Council Meetings, 1956-1970
  Contains minutes and correspondence relating to IFC meetings between 1956 and 1969. It has an incomplete file of lists of members of the IFC and individual members of the different religious organizations that belonged to the IFC. This series also includes minutes and correspondence relating to IFC sub-committee meetings, meetings of the Catholic Center, University Christian Foundation, and the meetings of the Directors of the various groups and of the Student Presidents of the individual groups.
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - IFC Meeting Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Member Organizations and Committee Member Lists, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - IFC Research Subcommittee, 1958, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Catholic Center Minutes, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - University Christian Foundation Meeting Minutes and Organizational Information, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Directors and Student Presidents Meetings, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Reports, 1957-1969, undated
  Consists of religious surveys of student religious life and organizations conducted by non-NYU sources, information pertaining to the religious preference cards distributed with registration materials and returned to the IFC, the two self studies (1956 and 1967-69) which profoundly affected the IFC, reports about the plans for a new tri-partite religious center, annual reports on religious activity at Washington Square, and a survey conducted by NYU of religious activity on other college campuses with brochures issued by these institutions.
  - Religious Surveys Conducted by Outside Organizations, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Religious Preference Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Self Study, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Self Study, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - New Religious Center, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports on Religious Activity at Washington Square, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Survey of Religious Activities on Other Campuses I, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Survey of Religious Activities on Other Campuses II, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series 4: Budget, 1957-1968, undated
  Contains correspondence and computer summary sheets of the yearly expenses and budget of the IFC. This series covers from 1957 through 1968, but it is not complete. Requisitions and invoices which contain substantive information and petty cash procedures are included. There is also a file of IFC magazine subscriptions and bills.
  - IFC Budget, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - IFC Budget, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Requisitions and Invoices, Petty Cash Procedures, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - IFC Magazine Subscriptions and Bills, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 5: Correspondence, 1956-1970
  Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding meetings, activities, publicity, and organizational details. It is arranged chronologically by year for the years 1956 through 1970. Correspondence for 1965 and 1966 is missing. There is a separate file for correspondence and copies of memos which were set aside for Dr. Isabel Wingate, a faculty member who was chairman of the IFC from 1963 to 1964.
  - IFC Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - IFC Correspondence I, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - IFC Correspondence II, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - IFC Correspondence I, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - IFC Correspondence II, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - IFC Correspondence, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Isabel Wingate, Faculty member and Chairman of IFC, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series 6: Activities, 1957-1970, undated
  Contains correspondence and publicity for the various activities run by the IFC. General publicity for the various religious groups at NYU is also included. Activities such as the IFC Dinner, Brotherhood Week, and the Art Shows have been placed in individual folders in this series. Annual calendars and weekly schedules for the IFC and Loeb Student Center are also included.
  - Activities, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Publicity for Religious Organizations at NYU, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Publicity for Religious Groups in Washington Square College Catalog, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Art Show, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Activities, Correspondence, and Publicity, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - UNESCO Citizen's Consultation Program, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Brotherhood Week, 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Brotherhood Week, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - IFC Dinner, 1957-1958, 1960-1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - IFC Dinner, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - IFC Dinner, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Information and Activities, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - IFC Weekly Schedules, 1960-1962 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - IFC Calendar, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - IFC Calendar, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Loeb Student Center Activity Schedules, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series 7: Personnel and Space, 1955-1970, undated
  Includes correspondence and memos regarding IFC employees (resident manager and secretary) and the use, maintenance, and security of 2 Washington Square North.
  - Personnel, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Room Use, Rules and Procedures, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Building Security, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Building Maintenance and Use, 1955-1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Building Maintenance and Use, 1966-1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Building Maintenance and Use, 1968-1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series 8: University Administration, 1957-1967
  Contains correspondence, mimeographed, and printed material from the university administration about general university matters.
  - University Administration Information, 1957-1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - University Administration: Memos and Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Reports of the (University) President, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - NYU Senate Report, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)